<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-03-16T07:04:10+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Morning Dev</title><subtitle>chronicles of my coding journey</subtitle><author><name>Davide Iaiunese</name><email>davide.iaiunese@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Google Developer Scholarship - a great opportunity to become a developer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018-03-10/gdswu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Developer Scholarship - a great opportunity to become a developer" /><published>2018-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018-03-10/gdswu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018-03-10/gdswu">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/google-scholarship.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Become a developer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to become a developer. I encourage you to look for new opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a job at the moment. The scholarship is still going on. I’m learning every day and having fun in the while. 
The main goal is always the same: to become a professional web developer. 
Keep that in mind. Always. Be persistent. Be patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are still in doubt, continue to read. What follows is my story with this scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-it&quot;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Google Developer Scholarship is a program sponsored by Google and taught by Udacity.
Together, they have one mission: to reach out as many people as possible and promote code learning. 
In fact this program is available for residents in EU, Russia, Israel, Egypt and my beloved Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire program consists of two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge&lt;/strong&gt; - or Phase One - and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nanodegree&lt;/strong&gt; - or Phase Two;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2017/2018 edition - the one I’m participating to - consists in four learning paths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web development&lt;/strong&gt; for beginners and intermediate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Android development&lt;/strong&gt; for beginners and intermediate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great thing about it is that this year’s edition offers more opportunities than ever before. As a matter of fact each track offered 30.000 spots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20.000 for beginners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10.000 for intermediate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, after this initial period, only top 10% students of each track could progress to the Phase 2. It means only 10% could access the full, six months-long program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So from the initial 60000 people &lt;strong&gt;only 6000&lt;/strong&gt; got to the second phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-applied-to-phase-one&quot;&gt;How I applied to Phase One&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an average October afternoon. I decided to check Facebook as it had been months since last time. I’m scrolling my feed and there I read about a Google Developer Scholarship opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application was due by October 15, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a big chance here. I could continue to learn web development, I thought, but with all the good that came with this. It meant persistent mentoring, a guided path, a guarantee to learn from the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, it was tough to think of a reason that would make me worthy of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I calmed down, reasoned. I made already the decision to commit to coding and don’t look back. I was well aware I would dedicate body and soul to it, if accepted. This is what makes me worthy of it, I realized. Commitment. I had nothing to lose. Everything to gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent the preceding weeks writing, deleting and rewriting my motivational letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October 15th arrived and it swallowed my application letter like a hungry, green blob. They inform me the selection result would arrive via email two weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh gosh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The longest two weeks of my life. There were only few, blessed moments when I was not thinking about the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that anxiety in my body I didn’t sleep well the night before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wake up, it’s 5 AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I Check my email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An hour goes by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I check again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anxiety rises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another hour. Still nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start to rethink my existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day goes on while nothing relevant comes into my inbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s 5 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhausted, I check again a last time. Finally, there it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/email-rejected.webp&quot; alt=&quot;GDN rejected email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rejected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/homer-heart-attack.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Homer heart attack&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could not avoid facing how sad I was about it. It was like I hit a wall with my bare face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most successful people met failure along the way, I thought, so I had to keep learning. I had to be strong, practice every day, all day long until I become good enough to get a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two days later I see this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/email-accepted-p1.webp&quot; alt=&quot;GDN Phase One - Accepted email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt like Homer here,  when he had a heart attack and was transition between his body and heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/homer-transition.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Homer transition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this day I imagine a scholarship selector sitting on a chair making an evil laugh a la Montgomery Burns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/mrburns.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Mr. Burns evil laugh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ive-learned&quot;&gt;What I’ve learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scholarship challenge altered the way I see web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered the other side of web development: to learn together with a community. It changed the way I see team work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you know why? Because good folks at Udacity decided to make participation to the community compulsory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning it bothered me because I’m introvert by nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to avoid social interaction when possible. Day by day though, I started to see the true potential behind it. I saw why Udacity wanted us to interact and help each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I learned cooperative learning, mutual help, contribution to open source project. I learned the power of improving with people is the core heart of web development. The best part of it to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I continued to learn alone I would have been a man in a cave who had never seen the world outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this experience I learned the most and quickest I ever did in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew both as a developer and as a person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that I am grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plans have changed. I don’t want to only become a professional web developer. 
I want also to be part of a greater reality than myself.
I want to be part of a greater community. 
I want to live a meaningful life. 
I want to help other developers. 
I want to grow together with and connect to people around the world with code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together is better indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There it was, Phase 1 finished. In two weeks we would have known who was going to Phase 2: the main dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-two&quot;&gt;Phase Two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 14th - Valentine’s Day - I received this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/gdswu/email-accepted-p2.webp&quot; alt=&quot;GDN Phase 2 - Accepted email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love you Udacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so euphoric to read that message that I jumped all over the house. My neighbors must have thought I lost my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-different&quot;&gt;What is different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participation to community is not compulsory anymore&lt;/strong&gt;. By this time everyone learned the value behind it;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A new, dedicated Slack workspace&lt;/strong&gt;. Recipients from all tracks converged here. Consider that there is 10% of the original 60.000 participants. It makes things way smoother. Also, community managers have an easier job to do now;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Each student has a mentor&lt;/strong&gt; who gives feedback on code, projects and the scholarship in general;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can take advantage of Udacity’s career portal&lt;/strong&gt;. It means we can receive 1 on 1 support to improve our professional profiles and prepare for interviews.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 15&lt;/strong&gt; is the ultimate deadline to finish the program. I can’t graduate if I don’t finish all the projects by then. It makes sense: we’re talking about a scholarship after all. 
Based on this there are &lt;strong&gt;recommended deadlines&lt;/strong&gt; to submit projects. 
I take them as compulsory so that I can avoid piling things up. Plus, it’s important to meet deadlines in a working environment. 
Once a reviewer accepts my projects I build my own version. For example, these days I’m building my own portfolio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-new&quot;&gt;What is new&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are already almost month into it and I am so excited for the weeks to come. There are initiatives coming up, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two &lt;strong&gt;webinars&lt;/strong&gt; on March 21 an 22 to talk about life after graduation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two &lt;strong&gt;hackatons&lt;/strong&gt; for Android tracks on April 14-15;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two &lt;strong&gt;hackatons&lt;/strong&gt; for Web development tracks on April 21-22;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our community managers will &lt;strong&gt;spotlight&lt;/strong&gt; the most outstanding students on a weekly basis. Read more &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/knowlabs.com/gdnd2017/updates&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see there are opportunities everywhere if you are serious about coding. Use socials too. That’s how I found out about this scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take the risk&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Davide</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ugh, another coding blog?! Why?!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018-03-06/issue1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ugh, another coding blog?! Why?!" /><published>2018-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018-03-06/issue1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018-03-06/issue1">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/issue1/hey-why-not.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Hey, Why not?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; another coding blog&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt; it’s from a regular dude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, up until not so long ago I was living the average life. I was average. The only thing I wanted was to just play it safe. I’m not proud of that at all, but to be honest I’m grateful I could go through that path because eventually, after living in Hungary in two different years (the first time as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/erasmus-plus/node_en?raw=true&quot;&gt;Erasmus student&lt;/a&gt;, the second as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://europa.eu/youth/eu/article/46/74_en?raw=true&quot;&gt;EVS volunteer&lt;/a&gt;, it brought me to the best a-ha moment of my life: when I discovered web development. It truly was that good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In code, I found what I didn’t elsewhere. I found freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;family-guy-explains-code&quot;&gt;Family Guy explains code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/issue1/family-guy-web-dev.webp&quot; alt=&quot;web dev described by Family Guy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture from Family Guy sums up pretty well what coding is in my own view.
Because just as Peter and Brian lure James Woods with candies as baits, code lures me (and hopefully you) with its languages and concepts. The only difference is that while James Woods gets trapped in a wooden crate - he stops eating candy - we can keep learning forever (I hope there is internet in Heaven).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s also part of the beauty behind code. When you think you know it all, when you start getting comfortable, that’s the time you start deprecating as a developer and realize there is so much more to learn. It rings a bell for me because I never liked monotony. Code offers the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enjoy-your-job&quot;&gt;Enjoy your job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came back home last summer, I had no options left but to look for a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at myself: what good could that bring in the long term? What’s the point of working all day long if you don’t enjoy it. 
I don’t get those who consider work just work: it represents how we spend a significant time of our lives. It’s how we spend most of our days. It must be invested in something we thrive to wake up to every single morning, if not most&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With “those” I don’t address the people who need a job, even if temporary, to escape a difficult situation. I don’t address them because they are the kind of people who have a goal in mind and work towards changing their lives for the good, they know well that their current job is indeed only current. I understand them. I did that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m addressing those who work for the mere purpose to make ends met. That’s takes a person to a mental breakdown down the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;Mission.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I ditched that. No more. No mas. Finish. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/italian-english/basta?raw=true&quot;&gt;Basta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did things in the wrong way too many times. I put others’ needs before me too many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is where I come from. That is where I don’t want to go back anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My purpose here is to document my journey from solo learner to professional web developer, I want to prove that it’s possible and that everybody can. And while I do it I want to contribute to community (our) learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2017 I decided to stop fouling myself. I decided to take responsibility for my life. I decided to pursue a career in web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A month later I was selected to participate in the Google Developer Scholarship challenge, along with other 20 000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, in mid-February, I was grateful to be one of the lucky 1% who was selected to receive the full scholarship, a six months long program covering web development widely. It’s teaching me to build responsive websites by using HTML, CSS, JavaScript and its advanced libraries such as jQuery and React.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;planned-contents&quot;&gt;Planned contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this blog I have many ideas in mind, all can be narrowed in the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;document the scholarship I’m in right now, the Google Developer Scholarship sponsored by Google and taught via Udacity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interviews with professional web developers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;walkthroughs on projects I built&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m truly excited for what’s to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Davide</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>